Guide to the Steven Moore Papers on David Markson,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Steven Moore Papers on David Markson,
1973-2010.
Moore, Steven, 1950-
2 linear ft. (1 record storage carton 1 document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1637
9707342
This collection documents the long personal and professional relationship between author David Markson and Steven Moore. Moore was Markson’s editor at Dalkey Archive, and friend and ally after the both ceased to be involved with Dalkey in 1996, the year the press brought out Reader’s Block. When Moore was still at the press they published Markson’s most critically acclaimed novel Wittgenstein’s Mistress in 1988, one of the first works of original fiction first published by the press, which before had been re-issuing out-of-print works.
Biographical Note
David Markson,1927-2010
David Markson was an American novelist working between the 1960s and his death in 2010. A long-time resident of New York City be received his Masters degree from Columbia in 1952. His work became more experimental over time with his most critically acclaimed novels being Wittgenstein’s Mistress (1988) and Reader’s Block (1996) both published by the Dalkey Archive press.
Steven Moore, 1950-
Steven Moore is an editor and literary critic. Much of his career, including his graduate work at University of Denver and at Rutgers focused on William Gaddis, whose letters he is now editing. He worked at the Dalkey Archive Press from 1988-1996 as an acquisitions editor and editor of the Review of Contemporary Fiction. From 1998 until 2010 he was a principle fiction buyer for Borders bookstores.
Scope and Content
The collection is primarily comprised of correspondence Steven Moore received from David Markson as well as publicity files, reviews of Markson's work, and Moore's collection of publications by Markson.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 3 series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1985-2010
Series II: Publicity Files, 1973-2007
Series III: Books
Subjects
Moore, Steven, 1951-; Markson, David.; Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Steven Moore Purchase 10/05/2012 2012.2013.M058
- Series I: Correspondence--Markson to Moore, 1985-2010
  This series is comprised of correspondence sent to Steven Moore by David Markson. The correspondence is sorted into material before, during, and after the time that Moore was Markson's editor at Dalkey Archive Press. The correspondence relates not only to editorial decisions, but also documents the literary opinions and everyday lives of the two men.
  - 1985-2010, (15 folders)
- Series II: Publicity Files, 1973-2007
  The publicity files series contains Moore's files of clippings, reviews, and publicity material related to Markson. Moore kept this file documenting Markson's career even after their formal editorial relationship had ended.
  - 1973-2007
- Series III: Books
  Books written by Markson and owned by Moore. Many of these are proofs, galleys, or inscribed to Moore.
  - Miss Doll, Go Home (Dell, 1965) inscribed to Steve Moore
  - Epitaph for a Dead Beat (Dell, 1961) inscribed to Steve Moore
  - Epitaph for a Tramp (Dell, 1959) with slide or cover image; inscribed to Steve Moore
  - Epitaph for a Dead Beat and Epitaph for a Tramp (Shoemaker and Hoard, 2007) bound galley
  - Going Down (Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, 1970) 1E HC; inscribed to Steve Moore; with DM’s annotations as copied from DM’s copy by SM
  - Springer’s Progress (Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1977) uncorrected; inscribed to SM (years later)
  - Springer’s Progress (Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1977) 1E HC; inscribed to SM; with DM’s annotations as copied from DM’s copy by SM
  - Reader’s Block (Dalkey Archive, 1996) 1E PB
  - Lesesperre (Solum, 1999) Norwegian translation of _____; inscribed to Steve Moore
  - This is Not a Novel (Counterpoint, 2001) with Markson’s annotation is margins (per SM)
  - This is Not a Novel (Counterpoint, 2001) uncorrected page proofs
  - The Last Novel (Shoemaker & Hoard, 2007) bound galley
  - The Ballad of Dingus Magee (Counterpint re-issue, 2008) with letter from Counterpoint
  - Confrontation no. 33/34 Fall/Winter 1986-87 (literary magazine of Long Island University” in which Markson’s story “Healthy Kate” appeared